Hello, good afternoon everyone. First of all, let me remind those of you who are computer science and engineering students, do you still remember what you need to do by tomorrow? You need to complete the pre-enrollment form. Alright, so one more time, if you are computer science and engineering student, you are supposed to complete the pre-enrollment form.
The problem is, if you don't complete it, then ARO will not help you to enroll in the required courses. So that may affect you. Something like you may not be able to complete your degree in four years. This is what I want to say. All right. Yeah. So please remember, you have to complete the form today or tomorrow. Good.
Okay, another thing is about lab number six. Lab number six is due on Wednesday next week, not this week. No worry. Okay, so lab six is due on Wednesday next week. So if you haven't yet started, you need to start because that may take you a bit of time to figure out the parameters, the weights and the biases. That is the lab about MLP.
multi-layer perception. All right. Wow. What's wrong? Hold in. I apologize. Holiday mood, huh? Midterm break. Oh, by the way, you are going to enjoy your midterm break very soon. Starting from coming Friday. Correct? Enjoy. Huh? Huh? Sorry? Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah. That's true.
You are going to deal with 2211 midterm after the break. The beauty is you have plenty of time to prepare it. Oh, but I know what you want to say, Desmond. If I could choose, I prefer you give me the midterm before the break, right? So you could really enjoy the break. I completely understand. Pros and cons, trade-off. You will see, this is live.
Because what I'm going to tell you today is you shouldn't pick the extremes, but pick something in the middle. I will tell you that very soon. Okay, so are you ready, everyone? We need to continue our discussion on multi-layer perception. I'm not sure whether we are able to finish everything today, but I will try. Good. Let's start.
Okay, we need to start from here. So last time, we finished talking about step one to step nine. Do you still remember what is step nine? Do you still remember? Let's check. Step nine, use the model. All right? So after you finish training the AI model, you finalize all the weights and the biases. It's time for you to make good use of the model. That means you do prediction based on
the weights and the biases that you fine-tuned. All right? So what is step number 10? Step number 10, you need to plot the confusion matrix. And by the way, what does it mean by confusion matrix? You want to produce a number of values to demonstrate in what situation the AI will be confused. And by the way, it's AI, not you. We are not given...
we are not giving you a plot to show in what situation you will be confused. Actually, we want to show a figure to demonstrate in what situation the AI will be confused. All right? Okay, so everyone, show time. You could call this guy, Confusion Matrix, by passing the expected output or the expected label.
and also the predicted labels to it. All right? And then you get back one thing called CM. CM doesn't mean centimeters, but confusion matrix. All right? CM would contain all the data. So what does it mean by all the data? Please take a look at the figure. So this is a confusion matrix. All right? Faster. Okay, good. A vertical axis. Vertical axis.
That means all this, right? All these are the actual labels. Actual labels. The vertical axis would be the actual label. How about the horizontal axis? Horizontal axis would be the predicted label. Predictable label. So what does it mean by 966? 966 means, well, you have 966 images that are classified as
Plus zero. But the actual labels are also zero. Ah, that means the AI does a good job. Do you know what I'm saying? So 966 here means you have 966 images that are digit zero. And indeed, you predict them as a digit zero. Okay? So let me...
take a look at another value. How about 1, 1, 2, 4? What does it mean by 1, 1, 2, 4? Okay, there are 1,124 images that are supposed to be digit 1. And indeed, you predict them as digit 1. Well done. Okay? One more. How about this one? This is 12, right? Eh, there are 12 images that are supposed to be digit 3. But...
The AI predict them as digit five. That means misclassification. All right. So this is confusion matrix. Confusion matrix gives you an idea how many images are misclassified and how many are classified correctly so that you know how to improve your model. All right. But apart from those numbers, you could see the figure.
It's in color, right? For those bigger values, you get back something brighter in terms of color. For those smaller values, you get back something in darker color. So what's the beauty of color? You highlight the important ones, right? So for human being, when you see something bright, then you pay more attention to it, right? This is the beauty of such a figure.
All right, then how do you call this figure? Heat map. Heat map. Heat map. Heat map is a table showing you values. And at the same time, with color. Brighter value means larger value. Right? Sorry, brighter color means larger value. Darker color means smaller values. All right. So how to come up with a heat map? You need to use another library.
called Seaborn. Seaborn is a visualization library that helps you to enhance the figure. And in fact, Seaborn is built on top of Mathplotlib. So from now on, especially for those of you who are going to do UROP, please make good use of Seaborn library. That will help you to produce something more impressive. And it shouldn't be very difficult for you. If you know how to do Mathplotlib,
then doing C-borne should be easy for you. All right? Okay, so let's take a look at the code. Okay, as mentioned, how to figure out all the numbers. You use confusion matrix, pass the actual labels as the first parameter, pass the predictor labels as the second parameters. And then you get back CM, which is an object that carries,
all the values. But you want to use Seaborn to make it colorful right? How to do it? First you produce a plot. How big it is? 9 inches times 9 inches and you get back the figure object and the access object. Okay now let's use Seaborn. The name of Seaborn is SN. Use Seaborn library called the heatmap function.
Then what do you need to pass to the heat map function? First, pass all the data. That means the data carried using the confusion matrix object. All right. And then you set annotate to true. So what does it mean by annotate to true? That means you want to show all the numbers in the figure. All right. So if you set it to force, you will only see the color, but not the numbers in the table.
If you want to show both the numbers and the color, you have to set the annotate to true. Okay? And one more, nine width. Wow. You could adjust the width of the nines in the figure. So if you want to have a thinner nine, you put a small number. If you want to have a thicker nine, then you put a bigger number. All right? Okay. And you want to show all the numbers in the table in decimal.
in decimal so that's why you put format equal d and then you want to make each cell in the figure a square that means the width and the height of the cell should be the same right okay square equal true and finally pass the access object to it so that we could make all the changes for you all right yeah hey remember you don't have to memorize all this
If we ask you to do something similar in the exam, we will give you the documentation. The most important thing is you know how to apply all those techniques. Okay? And don't forget you need to show the plot. Some of your seniors, they do seaborne, but they complain about, wait, I cannot see the figure. How come? Because they forgot to call show. They need to show the figure so that you will be able to see the colorful one. Is it okay?
Yeah? Good? Seaborn library. SN. Okay, one more thing. And you know what we expect you to do in lab 6? In lab 6, we really want to get you to read some of the documentations. Of course, it doesn't mean that if you don't understand the description, we ignore you. No. If you don't understand the description, please feel free to reach out to us.
And we are happy to explain you the details. Okay? But is it good to get you read the description? Yes. I know it's not easy. But this is good for you because one day, if you work in the industry, you are going to do the following. You do searching. You search for useful functions. And how to use those functions? You need to read the documentation page.
and see how we call the function and what parameters you need to pass to it. Okay? So you need to learn that. So I completely understand this may not be very easy for you at this point, but you could do it. If you encounter troubles, reach out to me. All right? Okay, confusion matrix. That's all. All right? Attention. Let me go back. Go back. More. Oh, good.
Hey, do you know why I want to show you this page? I am pretty sure that many of you are going to find an internship. And suppose that you are lucky, you get invited to an interview. Then before attending the interview, please do revision. You need to make sure that you understand all 10 steps. Because you may see something more or less the same. Most likely during the interview, you are given a data set.
and try to build an AI model to solve the given task. Then you need to go through all the 10 steps. So please allow me to do brainwashing. Let me go through the 10 steps one more time. First one, import all the required libraries. Step two, load the data sets. Probably the training data set and the test data set. Step three.
Remember, you have to explore your data. Without understanding your data, I don't think it's easy for you to do a good job. All right? And then step four, build the model. That means you build MLP, you add so many layers. How many layers do you need to add? And what are they? Right? Okay. Five, compile the model. I know many of you talk to a one-one.
midterm examination last Friday. Yeah? Hey. No worry. They are marking your answer script now. Okay. Step five. What does it mean by compile? Compile here has nothing to do about the compilation of the programs in C++. Compile here means you pick the optimizer. You pick the loss function. All right? This is what we mean by compile the model. And then,
train the model, and then evaluate the model, and then save the model, use the model, and finally, please plot the confusion matrix so that you know in what situation the AI will be confused. Hey, by the way, if we give you the confusion matrix, do you know how to compute? Precision? Recall? What's next? F1 score.
We could ask you to compute all of them. And suppose in the examination, we give you a confusion matrix, then we could get you to compute all of them and tell us whether the AI model is good or not. All right? So make sure you understand how to do all that. Good? Okay, keep going. Oh, okay, new stuff. Hey, for those of you,
who read the lecture notes that we prepared last semester, you don't see this. This is new material, okay? This is the new one. We would like to tell you one very important concept in AI and machine learning, batch size. So what does it mean by batch size? Showtime, wow. Actually, there are many different ways,
to do gradient descent. First of all, make sure that you know what is gradient descent. Gradient descent means you compute the gradient and then update the weights and the biases according to the gradient. Precisely, you need to update the weights and the biases in opposite direction of the gradient. Okay? Hey, how many different ways to do it? Mainly three. Batch.
gradient descent. This is the first one. Second one, stochastic gradient descent. We call this SGD. And then the last one, mini-batch gradient descent. Hey, could you guess which one is more common? One, two, or three? Could you guess? Just guess. Batch gradient descent, stochastic gradient descent, or mini-batch gradient descent.
The third one. The third one is the most commonly used. All right. So I will explain you all this. Are you ready? Showtime. So what does it mean by batch gradient descent? Listen carefully. You use all the data points in the training data set to figure out the gradient and then use the gradient to fine tune all the weights and the biases. Huh? Desmond, again?
Batch gradient descent means you use all the data points in the training data set. Okay? To estimate gradient and use it to fine-tune all the weights and the biases. Now, let me give you more details. Ready? Let's say you have 10 data points in the training data set. You get the first one, forward propagation. All right? And then you know the error.
Second point, you use the same set of weights and biases, forward propagation, and then you know the error. Third point, forward propagation, and then you know the error. Okay, time flies. The 10th data point, forward propagation, you know the error. You know the error of all 10 data points. Agree? You compute the average error. And then based on the average error, to figure out the gradient.
And then you update all the weights and biases now. Okay? Do you know what I'm saying? Then this is batch gradient descent. How many data points do you need to use in order to fine-tune all the weights and biases once? 10. If we have 10 data points in the data set. And let's say, if we do batch gradient descent,
I have 1 million data points in the training data set. Then how many data points do you need to use so that we could update the weights and the biases once? 1 million. Then this is batch gradient descent. Question. Is that the one that we have been using? No. No. Why? The one we have been using, yes. Listen carefully. We pick one data point.
forward propagation, and we use this point to figure out the error, and then to figure out the gradient, and update the weights and the biases. And then we use another point, forward propagation, and then we know the error. And we use it to figure out the gradient, and update the weights and the biases. This is what we have been doing. But the one that I mentioned earlier, batch gradient descent, is not the same. Do you know what I'm saying?
You use all the data points to estimate the error and use the average error to figure out the gradient and use it to update all the weights and biases. Okay, let me ask you this question. If you know how to answer this question, then I believe you get the idea. Okay, listen carefully. Training data set, 10 points. If I run batch gradient descent,
For fine tuning the weights and biases once, how many data points do you need to use? 10. Okay, next. If I do the one that we have been using, we have been using, if I have 10 data points in the training data set, to fine tune all the weights and biases, how many data points do you need to use? One. One. One. Okay? Do you know what I'm saying?
And so that's why batch gradient descent is not the one we have been using. But the one we have been using is actually stochastic gradient descent. Aha! The one we have been using is stochastic gradient descent. What does it mean? Listen carefully. We get one point from the training data set, forward propagation, and then we know the error. Based on the error, now we figure out the gradient. And use the gradient.
to adjust all the weights and the biases, backward propagation. Okay, and then we pick another point, forward propagation, and use the error of this point to estimate the gradient and use the gradient to find all the weights and the biases. So stochastic gradient descent is the one we have been using. It's the one that I used to demonstrate MLP earlier. Is it okay? Do you know what I'm saying?
Okay, now let me show you the third one. Mini batch, show time. Example, suppose I have a training data set, 64 samples. And suppose I use the batch size 16 for gradient descent. What does it mean by batch size 16? That means I'm going to divide the training data set.
into many, many different parts and each 16 points. Okay. Then how many parts do we have? For 64 points, 16, one part. Then how many parts? Math question. Four. 16 here, 16 here, 16 here, 16 here. Okay.
Batch size 16. So what does it mean by batch size 16? Listen carefully. We use 16 samples to compute the error. And then we compute the average error. Okay, now we figure out the average error of 16 points. We use it to estimate the gradient. And then we use the gradient to update all the weights and biases. All right.
Okay, and then we use another 16 points. We figure out the errors. We compute the average error and use the average error to compute the gradient and use the gradient to update all the weights and biases and so on and so forth. Do you know what I'm saying? Then this is mini batch. Good? Do you know what I'm saying? Okay, now, question. I have a lot of questions for you now. It's cool.
Very young. Ready? Batch size. 16. 32. Which one will let us update the weights and biases more? 16. Exactly. If you pick a batch size of 16, then you are going to update the weights and the biases more. More times.
Okay, so if you pick a batch size of 32, then you are going to update the weights and the biases fewer times. Okay, next question. In terms of the quality of the gradient, do you think the batch size 16 is better or the batch size of 32 is better? In terms of the gradient quality. 32, very true. Why? Because you use more points.
to figure out the gradient then it is more trustworthy okay are you ready more suppose you have a low-end computer what does it mean by low-end computer let's say uh you don't have a lot of rams you don't have a lot of memory okay in this case which one should you pick 16 or 32 as the best size 16.
Because you only need 16 samples to be in the memory at the same time. Then you can do the computation. Do you know what I'm saying? And you may say, come on, Desmond, only 16 samples. Even 32. It's just a few, right? No, no, no, no, no, no, no. Let me show you a crazy example. Suppose a one-sample data point could be one million dimensions. One million dimensions.
then can you see the difference? 16 and 32, which one is crazier? 32 is crazier, right? So you shouldn't assume that the input sample will be small, right? If the input sample is gigantic, then 16 and 32. And there is a big difference. Okay? Do you know what I'm saying? So that's why, starting from now, when you train a neural network, you need to set the batch size.
If you want to do the one we have been using, then you need to use batch size equal one. That means for each point, you will figure out the gradient and then you update all the weights and the biases. Okay, and we call this stochastic gradient descent. Okay, if you are rich, what does it mean by rich? You have a lot of RAM, you have a lot of memory, then you should do batch gradient descent. You use all the points to estimate
the gradient, and use the gradient to update all the weights and biases. But I don't think you could do it. The only guy who can do it probably will be Jensen Wang, the CEO of Nvidia, right? Do you know what I'm saying? So most likely, you should do mini batch. That means you pick a batch size, which is reasonable. What does he mean by reasonable?
your computer could handle. You have enough memory to load all those samples in the memory and do gradient estimation and do updating of weights and biases. Is it okay? Do you know what I'm saying? Three different ways. All right, one more time. The one we have been using is stochastic gradient descent. All right? But for rich guy, they should use batch gradient descent.
But for most people, they should do mini batch gradient descent. Good? Happy? All right. More, huh? Ha ha. Yeah. Here, I show you a comparison table. So basically, I compare small batch size and large batch size. All right. Hey, what does it mean by small batch size? Let's say 1 to 32.
But to be honest, batch size, normally we use power of two number. What does it mean by power of two number? Four, eight, next one, 16, next one, 32, 64, 128, 256, right? Normally we pick a batch size of power of two. Why? Because that would help you to fully utilize the hardware acceleration of your computers.
Okay, because your computer knows binary, right? Then if you pick a power of two batch size, probably we could optimize it for you, all right? So that's why most people, they pick power of two number as the batch size. Okay, what does it mean by large batch size? More than 256, all right? 256, 512, 1024, hey, 1024, next one. 20?
For eight. Thank you very much. Hey, by the way, if you are computer scientist, from now on, you should tell people 1K would be 1024. You shouldn't say 1K is 1,000. If you say 1K is 1,000, you are math guy. You are not computer science guy. Okay, let's see. In terms of speed, small batch size is slower. Okay, anyone here tell me why? Small batch size.
Then for one e-podge, you need to update all the weights and biases more times. Then it takes you more time to finish the processing. Agree? So that's why it's lower. But for larger batch size, it's faster. Why? Because you don't need to update the weights and the biases many, many times compared to small batch size. Do you know what I'm saying? Okay?
Suppose we only care about the time that we use to fine-tune all the weights and biases. Then I think using a small batch size is not a good idea. Using a small batch size, then you need to update all the weights and biases many times. Then it's slower. If you use a big batch size, well, then you don't need to update the weights and biases many, many, many times. Then it's faster.
Good? Okay, next. How about memory? If you use a small batch size, then you don't need to have a large amount of memory for that. Because small batch size means you just need to keep fewer samples in the memory at the same time. And that's enough. So the memory requirement is not that demanding. But if you have a large batch size,
then you need to have more memory. Because you need to keep more samples in the memory at the same time so that you will be able to figure out the error and then the gradient. Okay? So if you do not have a very good machine, you should pick a smaller batch size. Okay, how about gradient quality? I discussed about it already. Small batch size, the gradient may not be very good. Why?
Because you use fewer samples to figure out the gradient. That may not be very trustworthy. Some of them could be noisy, right? Okay, if you use a large batch size, you use more samples to figure out the gradient, then it's better. Okay, and finally, generalization. This is tricky, attention. So what does C mean by generalization? Generalization, that means...
whether you want to fine tune the AI model that works really well for training data set. Okay? If you use small batch size, then you may not come up with an AI model that work super well for the training data set. But this is good for what? For testing. Yeah? Because if you make your AI model works too well,
for the training data set when you see something special in the testing, you GG. So that's why we say that small batch size, better generalization because you don't follow the training data very well. Okay, how about large batch size? Well, if you use a large batch size, then your AI model would do relatively well towards the training data. Then you may get trouble.
when you see something different in the test data set. So that's why the generalization is not that good. Do you know what I'm saying? Okay? Why I show you this table, I want to tell you one thing. Trade off. Trade off. You shouldn't pick a batch size that is too small. You also shouldn't pick a batch size that is too big. So that's why I put this. The principle, not too big, not too small.
This is the rule of thumb. Never pick the extreme. Pick something in the middle. Sorry, everyone. I want to show you an example. I don't know whether you would agree, but this is what I believe. Is it good for you to take four credits per semester? Too few, right? But does it mean that you need to take 30 per semester? No, right? Same idea. So most people, if you take 15 credits per semester, that's good, right?
Not too big, not too small. What is the consequence for taking four credits per semester? Then very likely you are unable to graduate in four years. Then what if you take 30 credits per semester? Good luck. Good luck. It's easy to burn out, right? Yeah. So this is what I want to tell you. This is actually what we learn from AI. AI. Tell us all this, right?
You never pick something that close to the extreme. Too small, not good, too big, not good. Something in the middle, optimal. Oh no, by the way, you don't like it, huh? Sorry, I apologize. Sorry, sorry, sorry. Okay, then how do we set the batch size? Hey, everyone, some people, they want to know the hardware limit. What does it mean by hardware limit?
They want to know what is the largest batch size that their computer can handle. Interesting. Then they do this, right? They start something big. 512. Oh no, my goodness. Out of memory. Then they reduce it to 256. Wow, out of memory. 128. Still out of memory. 64. Okay. Then that's the limit. Wait, by the way.
This is not an excuse. You shouldn't start from 30 credits and see what's the limit. No. Okay. This is what I want to mention at this point. But to be honest, you may need to know the hardware limit. Listen carefully. If you care about the gradient quality, if you care about it, should you pick a batch size that is larger?
Yes, right? So that's why it's meaningful for you to know the hardware limit. The bigger, the better. In terms of gradient quality. Gradient quality. Agree? Yes or no? Happy? Okay. But some people, they do the opposite. They start from small batch size. 16? Yeah, okay. And then? 32? Yeah, still okay.
64, okay, 128, GG already. Okay, 64 is the optimal. So you could see different personality here. Some people start from large batch size and then reduce it a bit, a bit, and a bit, right? But some people do it in the opposite manner. Start from small one and then increase it, increase it, increase it. Yeah, up to you. Anyway, same thing. You want to know the hardware limit, okay?
All right? So my suggestion is the following. You better start from a smaller batch size and then increase it a little bit by a little bit. This is what I suggest you to do. All right? But if you see another instructor, they may tell you the opposite. Hey, stop from big one. Sorry. I shouldn't say bad guy, right? I should say that is not my style. Yeah? I play safe. Start from a smaller one.
And then bigger, bigger, bigger, and bigger. Good. Okay. Tuning for performance. As mentioned, I think most people, they use the batch size 32 as the starting point. And then they gradually increase it. 64, 128, and see what happens. All right. Good. Bring washing. More. All right. Look at my picture.
A batch size of 32 and 64. Which one run faster? 64. Then that means the bigger the batch size, the better the situation will be, right? You also increase the quality of the gradient. Why don't we simply pick a big one at all times? Exactly. You may not have enough.
RAMs to handle it. Okay? So that's why you need to test the limit. Do you know what I'm saying, everyone? Yeah? Okay? And suppose you know that your data set is very noisy. Then what should you do? Should you pick a larger batch size or smaller batch size? Larger. Subject to the amount of memory you have. Alright? So this is what I want to discuss with you.
All right? So these are all the things that you need to bear in mind when you fine-tune your AI model. All right? Okay. One more. Bring watching. We have three different ways of doing gradient descent. Which three? Batch gradient descent, stochastic gradient descent, and then mini-batch, right? Which one is the one that we used? Stochastic. But from now on, you should do mini-batch.
You should do mini batch from now on. Okay. Is it okay for you to do it for lab six? I think so. It should be okay. All right. Good. Okay. Now it's time to talk about different issues related to MLP. That means I will tell you there are a lot of troubles.
when dealing with mlp hey so far you see all the beautiful stuff right yeah makes sense hey desmond you only use one e-podge and then you could get 96 accuracy yeah very encouraging but life is difficult all right so let me tell you a number of issues that you need to handle for mlp as well as for other neural networks okay
These are the two potential problems that you may encounter when dealing with MLP and also for all the other neural networks. Vanishing gradient and exploding gradient. Vanishing gradient, that means your gradients are very small. If your gradients are very small, that means you don't put your weights and biases a lot.
In the worst case, you may stop turning your weight and the biases. Think about it. The amount of change for the weight and biases actually relying on gradients. If the gradients are too small, that means you don't change the weight and the biases. That means we cannot improve the model. Do you know what I'm saying?
How about exploding gradient? Exploding gradient, that means the gradients are super big. Super big, that means you are going to adjust the weight and biases a lot. Then you end up getting something super big. And the consequence will be you may not be able to store the weight and biases properly. Maybe overflow, maybe underflow. Do you know what I'm saying?
So remember, exploding gradient is bad. Vanishing gradient is also very bad. But you will encounter both from time to time. Believe me. Okay, now the question is, how do we know we encounter vanishing gradient and exploding gradient? All right, listen carefully. I will show you the details, but I will not give you the proof.
And I will also ignore the justification. Do you know why? Because I'm unable to explain all this to you without using calculus. I apologize. So if you want to know why, then you need to take 4211. Oh, by the way, some of you asked me, why I keep mentioning 4211 but not 3211? For those of you who are going to be major in...
AI, you need to take free AI courses for sure. First one, you are doing it now, 2211. Second one, 3211. Third one, 4211. Why I keep mentioning 4211 but not 3211? Does it means that 3211 is bad? No. The reason is in 3211, we focus on traditional AIs, like searching, okay?
And if you do Google search, you will see we talk about A-star algorithm, right? And then so on and so forth. Those are traditional AI. So if you only care about more than AI, then you may skip it. But if you want to be an expert in AI, you should take it. Do you know what I'm saying? Okay. And how about 4211? 4211 is something about more than AI.
Similar to 2211. So that's why I keep talking about 4211. All right. Anyway, let me tell you, how do you know you encounter vanishing gradient? If you see the parameters of higher layers very dramatically change a lot. Also, the parameters of the lower levels do not change a lot.
then most likely you encounter vanishing gradient problem. Okay, first of all, what does it mean by higher layers? Higher layers means those layers that are close to the output. How about the other one? Lower levels. Lower levels. That means those layers that are close to the input layer. Okay, so let me say one more time. If you see the parameters like weight and biases,
of the layers closer to the output vary a lot. But for those layers that near the input layers do not change much, then very likely you get vanishing gradient problem. Do you need to fix it? Let's say yes. And we will show you how to fix it later on. Okay? Vanishing gradient. But for exploding gradient, it's simple. All the model parameters
Grow exponentially. That means super big or super small. If you see some of them become NAN, then you know that you are experiencing exploding gradient. What does it mean by NAN? Not a number. That means that you cannot represent the number very well. Overflow, underflow. Is it okay? Remember, I only told you...
how to figure out vanishing gradient and exploding gradient. I do not tell you why, right? Because I cannot. If I need to explain to you all this, I have to do calculus. Hey, by the way, how many of you have finished multivariable calculus? Oh, very good. Then you should know this, right? If you deal with single variable calculus,
multi-variable calculus so that they are able to explain you the idea, right? No worry, I think the instructor will teach you that. But of course, if you have taken the multi-variable calculus course, congratulations, good job. Oh, by the way, how many of you took the calculus math exam on Sunday? Good. Oh, sorry. Sorry, I shouldn't ask. Bad guy.
Okay. These two are more important. Do you still remember I mentioned this? I said that you need to add a regularizer. You need to add a regularizer so as to avoid one trouble. Overfitting problem. So now, I would like to tell you what is overfitting and underfitting. The best way to explain these two ideas would be using a picture. All right.
We have been dealing with classification. We don't do regression at all, right? We only do classification. So let me focus on classification. So what does it mean by overfitting? Wow, this is overfitting. You try to train your AI model that work extremely well for your training data set. So even in your training data set, some of them are noise.
you still fine-tune the decision boundary to entertain them. Then this is overfitting. You see the decision boundary? Is it amazing? Absolutely amazing. Is this good? No. Why? If they are noise, and if you fine-tune your AI model that do very well for the training data points, then let's say during testing, if I get a point here, what would you say? Red or blue?
Red, but in fact, it should be blue. Then how do we describe this scenario? Overfitting. Overfitting. That means you tune your AI model that works too well for your training data set. When you see something different, or if you see something normal in the testing data set, you GG. All right? How do we know overfitting occurs? If you get a super good accuracy.
for training data, but get a not so good accuracy for testing data, then most likely you encounter overfeeding. Is it okay? Okay, analogy. Don't blame me. If I give you many, many past papers, then you train yourself to handle all the past exam questions very well. Is this good for you? May not be. Because if you give...
If we give you something different in the exam, right? So that's why we don't encourage you to do a lot of past exam questions. But does it mean that you do nothing? No, if you do nothing, you will get this, underfitting. What does it mean by underfitting? You just come up with something. That doesn't work well for training data either, right? Then we expect you will not do a good job.
for the testing data also right then this is ridiculous underfitting is ridiculous so do you think underfitting is popular or common no normally underfitting is not that common overfitting is common because you will do your best to get a reasonable good accuracy for your training data right so you never get overfitting almost right but remember overfitting is also very bad
Hey, Desmond, then what do you want? I want this. Optimal fitting. I know. I know what you're going to say. Rubbish, Desmond. Yeah, I know. Optimal fitting is good, right? That means you don't train your AI to work too well for training data so that even there are some noise. No problem. Optimal is better. Okay, another example to demonstrate, you shouldn't pick the extreme. Underfitting.
No good. Overfitting, no good. Somewhere in between is good. This is life. Same thing for you to deal with for your academic study. This is the beauty of learning AI. If you learn AI, you learn all this, right? Then you know how to manage your study. And at the same time, you know how to manage your life, right? Oh, by the way, let me tell you another thing. My classmate,
My former classmate, he said that life is just local optimization. Local optimization. What does it mean? Based on the current information, you pick the best. We never be able to do global optimization. If you want to do global optimization, that means you need to know the future. We are not fortune tellers, right?
Yeah, actually, I learned from him as well. Actually, he learned from AI. He learned from machine learning. Very interesting. Sorry, enough. I scared you. Good. Okay, again, how do you know you encounter overfitting? You have very good accuracy for training data, but not so good accuracy for testing data. Then very likely you encounter overfitting. How about underfitting?
Both are bad. Both are bad. The training data accuracy is low. Testing accuracy is also very low. Is it possible for you to see this? Training accuracy is very low, but testing accuracy is very good. Trimming, very unlikely. All right? The most likely, I mean, the reason could be there are bugs in your program.
I think that is the reason, right? Okay, now this is something more interesting. With Desmond, I know MLP is so powerful, but I don't know how many layers do we need to add into MLP? How many layers do we need? Okay, now let's talk about it. In an MLP, three types of layer, input layer, hidden layer, and output layer. Agree? So let's talk about...
Input layer, how many input layer? One, always. How many neurons in that layer? It depends on number of features for your problem. For example, if you are talking about exclusive or, how many inputs? Two, then two neurons. So I think in terms of the number of layer for input,
Very clear, one layer. How many neurons? Depends on the problem. Okay, how about output layer? How many? Always one. How many neurons? Depending on the problem. For handwritten digit classification, how many outputs? Ten. Ten probabilities, then ten neurons. Easy. What's the main trouble? Hidden layers.
Oh no, my goodness, Desmond, how do we know how many hidden layers we need to add? Here, I give you the rule of thumb. No guarantee, huh? If it doesn't work, don't blame me. No guarantee. Here, we just show you the rule of thumb. Okay, let's talk about the number of hidden layers. If your problem, that means the data is linearly separable, then the number of hidden layers will be zero.
No need. Have you seen that? Yes, right? If the data is linearly separable, you could use a perception. Perception. No hidden layer. Right? So first of all, check whether your data set is linearly separable. That means whether you could use a strict 9, a plane to separate the points into two groups. If you could, no hidden layer is needed. Enjoy.
Okay, let's say your data cannot be separate using nines or planes. Then you need to add some hidden layers, right? For problems that are not so complicated and has fewer dimensions, one to two hidden layers should be enough. But for some problems that are more complicated, or the number of features, sorry, or the number of dimensions of features,
It's large. Then you need to add three to five hidden layers. Okay? But once again, no guarantee. These are just rule of thumb. Good? Wait, Desmond. Even we know how many layers we need to add. Then how many neurons? This is crazy. Okay, let's talk about the number of neurons in each hidden layer. Normally, the number of hidden layer neurons would be
something between the size of the input and output. Okay, example. MLP for handwritten digit classification problem. What is the input size? That means the one after flattened layer. How many? 784. Okay? Input size, 784. How about outputs? 10.
then the number of neurons in the hidden layer should be something in between, between 784 and 10. So that's why we pick 128. We pick 128, something in between. Hey, is it okay for you to add 254? Oh, sorry, 256? Yes. Yes, also okay. But pay attention. If you add too many hidden layers, and if you add too many neurons,
you may encounter one trouble. Start with O. O-V. O-V-E-R. Overfitting. So it does mean that the more hidden layers you add, you get a better result. May not be. You may suffer from overfitting. All right? Same thing. Does it mean that the more the neurons you add, the better the performance you will get? No. You may get overfitting problem. All right?
Okay, there are some other researchers. They propose the number of neurons in the hidden layer should be number of inputs times number of outputs square root. No guarantee. Again, this is just a rule of thumb. This is a good starting point. You still need to fine-tune. What does it mean by fine-tune? Add more neurons.
reduce the number of neurons, and see what happens. Do you know what I'm saying? All these are just rule of thumb. Good? Happy? More? I love this. Attention. Suppose. Oh, sorry. Photos at the back. Could you see it? Especially this one. Could you see this? Wow, good. You are young, huh? Okay, suppose we have eight samples. Eight samples.
All of them are 2D points. Four of them are in one class. Another four in other class. That means only two classes, right? Four in class dots. Four in class cross, right? Okay. I want to find the decision boundary that separates them. Is this an option? Yes, right?
You could use a parabola to separate the points into two groups. By the way, why don't we use a strict 9? Is this linearly separable? No, no, no, no, no. Okay, so one option is to use a parabola. But in terms of parabola, there is another option. Agree? There are so many different parabola could be used. Okay, but this is good. Let me show you the beauty. Suppose...
I like this parabola. I want to use it to separate the points into two groups, right? I know that for this parabola, I could approximate it using two strict nines. Can you see that? To approximate the parabola, I can actually use two strict nines. Agree? Then so what, Desmond? Hey, hey, hey. One neuron. I could use it to come up with one strict nine.
I learned this from perception. Agree? If I put one neuron, I could use it to add a strict 9 in space. Okay, but we need to use another neuron to get another strict 9. Agree? So what I want to say, yes, if you need two strict 9s to approximate the parabola, why don't we add two neurons in the hidden layer? One neuron would give you one strict 9. Two neurons give you two strict 9s.
Okay, and then you add another neuron in the output layer to connect them, to connect the two straight nines. But Desmond, what are you talking about? I just want to tell you based on the 2D plot. I know how to design my MLP to solve it. But this works, given that you could plot the data. That's why I have been encouraging you to
To plot your data, to explore your data, right? Wait, by the way, if your data set has 2D points, you should definitely plot them. Because this is doable. By plotting all the 2D points, you know what kind of decision boundary could use to separate them. Agree? Then you know how to design your MLP to solve it. How about 3D? You could. How about 4D?
Forget about it. 5D, dreaming. 6D, go to sleep. But 2D, 3D, you should definitely plot the data points. If you don't do so, you're lazy. Do you know what I'm saying? So let me tell you what we could do in the exam. We could give you, let's say, 10 points. And then you should plot the 10 points in space and see what kind of...
Decision boundary could be used to separate them. Then next, design a suitable MLP to solve it. We could give you a question like that. Okay? What we need to give you is, you are given this data set. Please design an MLP to solve it. Okay, one more. Are you with me? If you know, these two nines could be used to approximate the parabola.
Do you know how to set the initial weights and biases? Do you know how to set the initial weights and biases? I think so. You could definitely set something interesting so that you could get the answer quickly. All right? That means if you could plot the figures, you have a lot of things to do. If you cannot plot, no. All right? Good? Happy? Oh, no. I scare you.
Okay, more. All right. Now, I want to show you the role of weights. Wow, Desmond, you put weights, you put biases in MLP, right? Now, I want to know what is the role of weights. I think the best way to figure it out would be this. Assume that I only have one neuron. One neuron, one bias. Agree?
inputs only, then only one weight. And why I use one neuron to figure out the role of weights? Because one neuron, simple enough, one neuron with one bias, one input with one weight, all the things are very simple. Then it is easier for us to figure out the role of weights, right? Okay, and then assume that we use sigmoid activation function.
So in order to figure out the role of weights, I do this. I keep changing the weights, but I don't change the theta. Why I don't change the theta? Because theta is not what I want to know. What I want to know is the role of the weight. So that's why I keep changing the weights, but I keep theta remain unchanged, right? Okay, wow. Then we plot the outputs.
Obviously, the output should look like what? Sigmoid function. Because you need to pass the weighted sum to activation function so that you get the output, right? So, not surprisingly, you get a whole bunch of sigmoid. But for the red one, you set the weight to 0.5. Green one, you set the weight to 1. Blue one, you set the weight to 2.
Black one, you set the weight to three. What could you see? The weight control the slope of the middle region of sigmoid. Right? The bigger the weight, the steeper the slope would be. Right? So in other words, the weight would control the stiffness of the middle region of the sigmoid. Is it okay? Could you see that? All right. And let me finish the next slide. And then I shut up.
Shut up. Yep. Okay, now let me show you the row of biases. Same thing. One neuron, one bias. One input, one weight. We use sigmoid as the activation function. Okay, this time I fix the weights as one. But I keep changing the biases. Zero, one, two, three. What could you see? Of course.
you still see many sigmoid functions, but different biases, you shift the sigmoid function to left and right. All right? Red one, if the bias is zero, that means you get the original one, original sigmoid function. Okay, green one, you set the bias to one. Blue one, you set the bias to two. Black one, you set the bias to three. Okay?
Listen carefully. If you set the bias to 1, you shift the whole curve to the left by 1 unit. How about bias equal to 2? You shift the whole curve to the left by 2 unit. More question. What if I set the bias to minus 1? Shift the curve to the right by 1 unit. No excuse. If we ask you this question in the exam, you should know what to say. All right? So basically, the bias is,
are used to shift the activation function. But the weights are used to adjust the stiffness of the middle part of the sigmoid. Okay, I think I better shut up. Wow, very good. We are now going to see each other on Friday because you should enjoy your midterm break. All right, have a nice midterm break. Everyone, see you after the break.