Hello everyone. Good morning. Happy New Year. Wow, we are in the year of the horse. Yeah, should be a good one. I guess, yeah, the majority of you are still in your hometown, right? Yeah, I completely understand. But thanks for coming, especially it's in the early morning, 9 a.m. Good.
Hey, but the first thing I would like to tell you will be lab two. The very first hanging lab. Hey, what does it mean? Lab one is just something to help you to warm up a little bit. Right? What is it about? Lab one? Lamp high. Lamp high. I do encourage you to try tackle the problems that we gave you. All right?
That one should be something about image processing, simple one. So basically we ask you to load an image using a library, all right? And what you obtained will be a numpy array and try to manipulate the numpy array. So that would be something very similar to what you did in COM1023, all right? Hey, by the way, how many of you took COM1021? Oh!
Okay, good. No worry. This is what I'm planning to do. I will probably post my lecture videos for you. What videos? Those that I gave to COM102 free students. Do you know what I'm saying, everyone? Of course, I'm not going to release all the videos. I will only release those that are important for you.
For example, Lumpie, Pandas, etc. But do let me know. If you want to watch all of them, let me know. I'm happy to release all of them for you guys and girls. Is it okay? I'm very eager to help you out. So even if you didn't do Lumpie, Pandas before joining us, it's okay. No worry. We will help you out. Okay? Hello, good morning.
This is the first Hengin lab. It is about naive Bayes classifier. That means the one that you have been learning. All right. We will ask you to tackle this problem using lumpy from scratch. In other words, you are not allowed to use Psyche Learn. Sorry, because we gave you the code already. If you refer to the lecture notes.
We gave you one. The one is implemented using scikit-learn. All right. And in the lab, you need to deal with something very similar, but this time using lumpy library. But what I recommend you to do is to cross-check the answer using scikit-learn. Do you know what I'm saying, everyone? You should implement this using lumpy. But please...
make changes to the code given to tackle this problem and check the answers. If they are more or less the same or very close to each other, that means you are good. This is what I recommend you to do. Very easy. You just copy the code and modify a few lines and then you should be able to get the correct answer. All right? Is it clear? Okay, this lab, we will release it this evening.
Ah, it's not yet released. At each time we release something new, we will definitely drop in email to let you know, wow, you have something new to tackle. All right? And we will take a final look and make sure that everything that we post online are good. Is it okay? Yeah? You have two weeks time to tackle this lab. Ah, just like Commodore 2.3, right?
Once we release the lab, then you spend some time, right? And compare the answers with your classmate. I don't know. So make sure you do the right thing. Good. Okay, we are going to finish NaiveBase today and start a new topic. But before we cover the last part of NaiveBase, let me ask a few questions. The first one, NaiveBase, right?
Is this something that we use to tackle supervised learning or unsupervised learning? Is it a supervised learning method or unsupervised learning method? Supervised. Because you need to have a labeled data set. Exactly. Just like the disease problem, right? You have a data set with symptoms and whether the guy...
is suffering from disease Z, right? So it is a labeled data set. Remember, we have been dealing with problems using supervised learning. This is very important. Okay, and what are the naive assumptions that we have been using? Given the belief, all the evidence are independent.
That means they're not related to each other. But remember, this is nonsense. This is not true in most circumstances. But we still make this assumption in order to simplify the formula a little bit. And is it possible to get 0 for some conditional probability? Yes. Why? Because?
You cannot find any data, okay, for that in the data set. Whoa, that means you need to do counting, right? But when you check the data set, none of them match, right? Then the counts will be zero. Then the counts will be zero. And this is what we mean by zero frequency problem, zero frequency problem. Then how to tackle it? We introduce you one way to tackle this problem, right?
What's the name? Alpha Laplace moving. What is the typical value of alpha? One. But the one that we put in the example is a very small value. That is something very close to zero. Why? We actually want to set it to zero, but we cannot. Right? Scikit-learn will not allow us to set the alpha value to zero because we may get zero frequency.
trouble. Alright? So, I really want to say it to zero, but I cannot. So, that's why I set it to something super tiny, super small. Okay? And by the way, this is exactly what you need to do at home. You need to do revision. Try to get familiar with all the things that you learned so far. Alright? And because many of you, especially your seniors, they ask how to get a good grade in 2211. Revision.
You need to be familiar with all the concepts. Almost at any time. All right? And from now on, start thinking about how to tackle problems using the approaches that we introduce you. For example, you may want to explore interesting data set online. Yeah? And use some of the methodologies that we introduce to tackle them. All right? Is it okay? All right. Then it's time to...
Cover the remaining materials. Stir. Yes. Okay, this is where I stopped last time. I guess all of you received my emails, right? I dropped your emails in the midnight. Yeah, during the Chinese New Year. Yeah,恭喜發財. Very good. And basically, the emails are about a naive base. So what I want to emphasize here would be...
You calculate the numerator values. The numerator values for yes and no. That means a given disease equal yes and given disease equal no. And see which one is larger. And in this example, which one is larger? Which one is larger? This is given disease equal yes. Given disease equal yes.
Given disease equal no. Which one is larger? Don't scare me. Which one is larger? Just check the value. Given disease equal no. Given disease equal no. So that's why you say for this patient with the list of symptoms, I think it's unlikely for him or her to suffer from the disease Z.
But we normalize it. What does it mean by normalize? That means the posterior probability for disease equal no divided by the sum of the two numerators. What does it mean by the sum of the two numerators? The sum of the two numerators. What does it mean? That is actually the denominator.
we have been ignoring. So this is what I mentioned in the email. One more time. You see that we normalize it, right? We do this. The posterior probability divided by the sum of the two numerator values. The sum of the two numerator values are actually the denominator that we have been ignoring. Bear this in mind. So this is what you need to bear in mind.
Good. Hey, by the way, how to make this problem more tedious? And for example, I'm a bad guy. If I want to give you something more tedious in the exam, then what is the best approach? More symptoms and more beliefs. Ha, then I could keep you busy, right? And for more beliefs, then you need to compute more numerator values. More symptoms, then you need to do...
More counting. Do you know what I'm saying? So this is something that you may explore. Because many of your seniors, they ask, before the medium examination and final examination, what to do? You need to keep thinking what we may do in the exam. So get prepared. Okay. Now, new stuff.
This is the naive Bayes formula, right? So what does it mean? This is the numerator part, and we need to compute all the numerator parts and see which one is the largest. And then we get back the corresponding belief, right? Why I show you this formula one more time? Because of this formula, you need to multiply all the conditional probability.
Yeah, this one, multiply this one, multiply this one, multiply the last one. And you also need to multiply the prior, right? You multiply all this together. And remember, each of them is a value in range zero and one. Each of them is a value in range zero and one. And if you try to multiply many values in the range zero and one.
what happened? This one in the range 0 and 1, another one, another one, and another one, multiply all of them. What happened? You are going to, or you may get a very small value, right? Attention. And even this formula is a very good one, but if you try to multiply many values,
or in the range 0 and 1, you may get something extremely small. Then what's wrong with it? The bad thing is you may get underflow error. What does it mean by underflow? That means the value is super small, so we may have trouble representing it using our computer. Yeah? Wow, because the value is super small. I don't even know how to represent it precisely using our computer.
So this is an underflow error. Then how to avoid this trouble? Simple. Hey, math stuff, huh? High school math. Everyone, are you ready? For example, you have two values, a, b. A times b. A times b. Do you still remember if we take log, what happens? If you have two values, a times b. And then you take log. Log a, b.
Then log A plus log B. Wow, Desmond, how come you talk about high school math? How come you talk about logarithm? The reason is AB could be values in range 0 and 1, right? And I know that if we multiply them, we may get something very small. The trick is you take log. If you take log, it will be converted to log A.
plus log B. That means I convert a multiplication problem to an addition problem. Multiplication, wow, you may get something extremely small, but doing addition, you will not get the same trouble. Do you know what I'm saying, everyone? So most people, they do it in this way. We still calculate the numerator, but instead of doing multiplication of probabilities, they take log. They take log.
Desmond, I don't understand you. What does it mean? That means that you still compute the conditional probability, but you take log. And they add up all of them. And you also take log for the prior. Add it in as well. And same goal. I want to see which belief would give us the largest logarithm value. Largest logarithm value.
Everyone, one more time. How to solve the problem using naive Bayes? Likelihood. Conditional probability, right? The first one, the second one, the third one, all of them. And then, take log for each of them. Add them up. And then see which one gives you the larger value. And that would be the best, so-called best belief. Right? That means the one that is more likely to occur.
Yeah, it's so nothing very interesting here. I basically just tell you hey don't do multiplications do log and additions This is the implication everyone. Yeah, so in lab 2 you need to do exactly the same thing You may ask Desmond. I don't know how to take log in Python interesting You need to use math library in Python, right? So laptop you do counting and then you get a
conditional probability and then take log and then add up all of them and see which one gives you the largest value and then I think that belief will be the best one. Is it okay? Good? In the exam if I ask you why we take log you should say well we want to avoid underflow error, underflow error because by multiplying whole bunch of conditional probabilities
that are in the range 0 and 1, we may get something extremely small that would give us trouble in representing the value precisely. Is it okay? Yeah? Underflow, error prevention. Nothing new. Just simple messed up, right? Okay. All right. Now, let me tell you what are the applications of NaiveBase. Wow, Desmond, you stupid.
Because you mentioned that all those are naive assumptions. You shouldn't make naive assumptions. So even we could simplify the formula quite a bit, but you make naive assumptions. Then I don't think there is a good one, no application, right? No. Even we make naive assumptions, which is not realistic. But still many people use it. Why? They get pretty good results for some reason.
So what are the applications? The first one is real-time prediction. Because Naivebase runs fast. How come? Because we could pre-compute all the conditional probabilities. So if we get more information from the user, we could compute everything fast. So if you want to come up with a system that could respond in real-time.
then you may consider using naive base. Second thing, multi-class prediction. So what does it mean by multi-class? Another word of belief. If you don't want to use the word belief, you may use the word class. Multiple beliefs, multiple classes. So naive base can be used to deal with multiple class problems. For example,
given your assessment score, what would be your grade, right? Multi-classes, multiple beliefs problem. Yeah, because for some methodology, they could only be used to tackle, let's say two beliefs. No more than two, right? But naive base, no problem. Multiple beliefs, multiple classes. Okay, text classification. Text classification, what does it mean?
And Naivebase has been, we have been using Naivebase to tackle text-related classification problems. For example, spam mail detection, spam email detection. While given an email, whether this is a spam or not, people have been using Naivebase to do it. Yeah? And also, if you want to categorize a piece of text, okay?
Yeah, whether this is a piece of text about adventure, about love story, about this and that, you could use Naivebase. Very common. Okay, and then recommendation system. If you want to provide some recommendation to people, you may use Naivebase as well. All these are common applications. All right? Yeah? So this is real.
This is not just a toy. And many of your seniors, they say that, hey, Desmond, you start from Naive Bayes. That means that this is a toy algorithm. Not really. This is something real. This is something that people have been using. And you are going to tackle another problem in lab two, using Naive Bayes. And then you will see why this guy is interesting. Okay, advantages and disadvantages of Naive Bayes. Hey, starting from now.
we will discuss the advantages and disadvantages of each approach. Why this is important? Because without discussing the advantages and disadvantages, we don't know which one to use to tackle the problem you have in hand, right? We are going to talk about more and more algorithms. But after we finish each one, that's the time to talk about the advantages and disadvantages. Okay, advantages.
Very easy to implement. What? Desmond, I don't think that's easy. Then let me put in the word relatively easy. This is a relatively easy to implement algorithm compared to the others that you are going to see. Huh? This one is easy already? Yeah, pretty easy. Okay, it has a computational efficiency. That means fast. Yeah?
Not very expensive. You can compute everything fast. Okay, it works well on a large size data set. Very true, because basically you just do counting. So even the data set is very big. I don't care. Still very fast. And by the way, in lab 2, no follow. No wow look. You need to do counting using Lampoi. Very interesting.
But if you cannot tackle the problem, reach out to us. We could give you some hint. Yeah? And we are good guys. You will believe. We could give you some hint. And then you will say, yeah, okay, I know what to do. Desmond, thank you very much. Then you go home and tackle the problem. All right. Okay. It also can be used to predict multiple classes. This is what I mentioned earlier. Multiple class.
Problem, no problem. Okay, and it has been used to tackle natural language processing text classification. All these are not new. We mentioned them earlier. Okay, let's talk about disadvantages. The first one, we made naive assumption and assumptions are not realistic. Yeah, we know. But still, practically speaking, not bad. I mean, the result is not bad.
Okay, if the data set is very small, then the prediction may not be accurate. But this is not the only problem for naive Bayes. This is actually the problem for all the remaining algorithms. If you have a small data set, that means that you don't have many information in hand, right? Then the prediction may not be accurate. So I would say this is not the only problem for naive Bayes, but we need to mention it. Okay.
And if you are dealing with regression problem instead of classification, then naive base is not a good one. Everyone, let me give you the intuitive idea. I've been saying making naive assumption is naive. Making naive assumption is naive, right? That means not good. But how come people still use it? The reason is very simple. Intuitive idea. For example, one numerator.
is 0.6. Another numerator is 0.4. Okay? But if we don't make naive assumption, maybe the first one should be 0.7. Another one should be 0.3. But even the numerator values are not that accurate. But you still do the prediction, I mean the classification correctly, because you pick the larger one, right? Do you know what I'm saying? So,
This is why people, they still use it. Even naive assumptions are stupid. Let me say one more time. For example, by making naive assumption, you compute two numerators, right? The first numerator is 0.6. The second one is 0.4. So you say that, the first one is better with a larger numerator value. Agree?
But without making naive assumption, let's say the correct value of the numerator should be 0.7. This one should be 0.3. As you can see, we still do classification correctly because we picked the larger one, which is 0.6. That means the classification is still okay. But if you do regression problem, that means you want to get a real value as the output.
Then let's say the real value 0.6 and 0.7 is quite bad, right? With a 0.1 off from the correct value. So this is the intuitive idea for this one. If we do regression problem instead of classification, naive base is not good, right? Do you know what I'm saying, everyone? Yeah? But classification is acceptable because with tolerance.
Hmm, the probability values a little bit off. No problem, we still do the classification correctly somehow. Do you know what I'm saying? Yeah? Okay, and then the last one. We may get a zero frequency problem, but we know how to tackle it, right? We could do alpha Laplace moving. Yeah? I'm not saying we will give you essay type question, but you should understand all the pros and cons of each approach.
that we are going to introduce you. Is it okay? Yeah? All right, question. If I have a problem to tackle, the output should be a real value, not just classification. I want to use AI to tackle a problem, and then the result should be a real value. Then do you think naive base is a good one? No, right? This is why you need to understand the pros and cons of each approach. I will definitely drop this guy. But somehow,
Now I'm tackling a classification problem. Then I think naive base is reasonable in most circumstances. All right? So far so good? Happy? Okay. Eh, hey, practice problem. Apart from the disease, Z problem, we give you another one. Eh, what is it about? You see, animals, size, color.
The first three, animal, size, color. Those are evidence. And then the belief will be, can we pet them? So is this a label data set? Labeled data set, right? Because we have all the inputs, that means evidence, and then the expected output. Belief. So try to tackle this problem using Naive Bayes.
Remember, you don't have to compute all the conditional probabilities because I just asked you to answer this question. For a new animal, the animal is cow, the size is medium, the color is black, can we pet it? Just based on the given data set, answer this question using naive Bayes. Okay, do counting. Please try this at home and we...
gave you the answer already but don't read the answer. Tackle the problem first and check your answers. And I also give you the scikit-learn implementation for this problem. Okay? Good? And I think I mentioned this last time, right? During the Chinese New Year's Eve, I will give you another one that you need to apply the Gaussian stuff. Gaussian.
That means a continuous data instead of categorical data. Hey, by the way, for this problem, do we give you categorical data or numeric data? Categorical, right? So this is simpler. But I may give you one with a mixture. That means some categorical, some numeric, and do naive base. This is possible. And even if it is more tedious, I know. But still good, interesting.
All right? Good. Okay, then. Let's start a new topic. All right, this is topic number three. Yes. And once again, this is a supervised learning algorithm. Supervised learning algorithm. That means I will still give you the expected output. I will still give you a label data set.
Hey, but what is k nearest neighbor classifier? Hey, easy, huh? Everyone, show time. Input, input, input, input, input, input, input. Huh? Hey, Desmond, what are you saying? I have seven points. Seven points. Seven input data points. And each data point,
representing some evidence. For example, each input data point will be 2D, right? 2D, that means the two value. Those are evidence. And how come two different symbols? Some are crosses, some are dots. Because for these three data points, one category. For these four data points, another category. All right?
Okay, now the question is really simple. If I have a new one right here, if I have a new one, new input data point, circle, then which category should it be? Which category should it be? Is it a cross or a dot? Okay, one more time. I have some data points in hand. These three belong to the same category.
These four belong to the same category. All right. And now I have a new one. I want to know which category should the circle input data point be. Okay. The methodology is really, really simple. Everyone, are you ready? I, let's say, find the nearest three.
I find the nearest three data points. Oopsie. Interesting. Okay. I find the nearest three data points. That means this one, this one, and this one, right? I think the nearest three data points to the circle one will be this one, this one, and this one. Agree? And then I says that majority voting.
Let me follow the majority. Among the three, two says cross and one says dot. Then what should we say for this one? Should we say that it is in category cross or category dot? Cross. Cross. Because the three nearest neighbors, two of them are cross. And only one of them is dot.
Then I follow the majority. Yeah! Peer pressure. Right? This is what we have been doing. Agree? So this is three nearest neighbors. And from now on, I will tell people how to tackle this problem. I used three nearest neighbors to determine the category of the new one. Okay, so what does it mean by k nearest neighbors? That means...
I take a look at the K nearest one and do the majority voting and then follow the majority. By the way, is this simple? Yeah, very simple. Very simple methodology. I think this is something simpler than naive Bayes. Because for naive Bayes, you need to do calculation, right? This one, you also need to do calculation. But it should be simple, right? How to measure whether which are the nearest?
How come we say that those three are the nearest? Based on what? The distance, right? Because these three are closer to this one in terms of distance, right? So in KNN, K nearest neighbor, you only need to compute the distances. Distances? What do you know about distances? Distance formula, right?
I think the distance formula is the one that you have been using. But in this course, we will introduce you more distance measure, more distance metrics. Okay? Other than the one that you learned in high school, we will tell you more. Hey, by the way, do you get the idea? Pretty easy. Yeah? Okay.
Hopefully you get the general idea. And from now on, before I talk about the details of the algorithm, I will first show you the intuitive idea. Okay, now, hey, similar to Naive Bayes, before we talk about the algorithm, we give you a problem. Hey, what's the problem this time? Are we going to deal with disease? Z problem? No, not medical problem. Because we are still developing the medical school, right? Let's do that later.
Then now, let's tackle T-shirt problem. A T-shirt? Suppose we have the heights and weights of customers. The heights and weights of customers. And we also know that their T-shirt size. Desmond, I don't know what you're saying. Elaborate. For example, customer one, the heights, 158.
Weight, 58. He saw her t-shirt size, medium. So these two will be the input. This one will be the expected output. Right? Okay, customer two, 158 will be the height. 59 will be the weight. Medium t-shirt size. Okay, let me show you one more. Ah, this guy. Height, 170. Weight, 68.
T-shirt size, large. Hey, let me motivate you a little bit. Why this problem is interesting. Suppose I'm running a factory and I'm only able to produce two different size of T-shirt, medium or large, because I'm poor. I cannot manufacture many different sizes of T-shirt, only two types, medium or large.
Then I want to know whether I should give a medium-sized t-shirt to this guy or a large t-shirt size to this guy. Then now, the measurement will be height and weight. But I want to do it using AI. Okay? So that's why we come up with this problem. Is it okay, everyone? Once again, is this a labeled dataset? Yes. Why? Because weight and height, height and weight are inputs.
And then we also know the corresponding teacher size, which is the expected output. So this is a labeled data set. That means we are going to do supervised learning. And we are going to tackle this problem using k nearest neighbors. I keep saying k nearest neighbors, k nearest neighbors. Very tedious. From now on, I will call it KNN. Why? Lazy.
If you talk to people, K-N-N, K-N-N, K-N-N, K-N-N, they should know. Because all of them are lazy. Don't say K-nearest neighbors. Yeah, you're good, huh? But you will only do it during the interview. Because you want to show that you really understand what is K-N-N. But in most circumstances, you say K-N-N. K-N-N. So far, so good? Okay, now. Showtime. K-nearest neighbor.
I love this picture. This is something very similar to the one that I drew earlier, right? Hey, by the way, how many different shapes are there? Triangle, square, and circle, right? Triangle, circle, and square. That means three classes of three beliefs. How come we plot something?
On 2D planes, 2D plane, 2D plane, that means each point, two values, X and Y. Those are the inputs. Those are the inputs. Oh, that means we have some evidence in hand representing as points. Each point, 2D, two values. Just like weight and height, weight and height, weight and height. Ayah, the customer, weight.
and height, then two values, two values, 2D points. It could be medium or large, right? That means different category, different belief, different shape. Okay? Anyway, this one is more complicated because there are three categories, triangle, square, circle, right? Okay? Now, all these are the ones in the data set.
Okay. The real question is, now I have this one. What class should it be? Or what category should it be? Then we says that, let's find how many nearest neighbors. If we only care about those in the circle. How many nearest neighbors? Five, one, two, three, four, five. Okay, five of them. We find the five nearest neighbors.
and then we do majority voting, we follow the majority, then what should we say about the red circle point? That should be triangle, should be triangle category. Yeah, because two of them are circle, two of them are triangle, one will be square. By the way, wait a minute, why we pick triangle? Why not circle? Yeah, actually I love this picture because
This gives you something to think about. Five nearest neighbors. Two are triangle. Two are circle. One is square, right? I shouldn't say the red one should be square. No, there is the minority. But in terms of the majority, two different ones, triangle and circle, right? Then which one should we pick? This is a tie. Which one should we pick?
Let me tell you how to resolve this later on. But you get the idea. You get the idea? Okay, good. I have a tricky question to ask you. If you know how to answer this question, I will be super happy. For a problem with only two categories, for a problem, the expected output, only two categories, then what would be the best value of K? Because I want to avoid a tie.
Odd number, exactly, right? For a problem with only two possible categories as the expected output. Either A or B. Either A or B. Yeah? Hey, I want to use a K nearest neighbor. Then I will say the value of K. That means the number of nearest neighbor. It's better to be an odd number. Odd number, no time, right? There should be a winner. Hey. So this is actually something that I may ask you in the exam.
Yeah, based on certain situation, I ask you, what should be the value of this one? Why? But how come it doesn't work? Even we pick five, five nearest neighbor is an odd number. How come it doesn't work for this problem? Three classes, three categories, right? It doesn't work. Even you pick odd number, GG. Yeah, so we need to come up with some way to resolve the,
That means if there is a tie, we need to somehow figure out which one is the ultimate winner. Is it okay? Do you know what I'm saying? Okay, now, let me go through all the bullet points. KNN is the one that is a very popular machine learning algorithm. Why this guy is super popular? Because easy. Very easy.
Easy to understand, very intuitive, easy to implement, et cetera, et cetera. This is even simpler than Naive Bayes, right? Because Naive Bayes, you need to do counting, you need to compute the conditional probability. Oh yeah, it's killing me. But KNN, simple, easy to understand, right? Okay, and KNN is a lazy learning algorithm. What does it mean by lazy? Everyone, attention.
What does it mean by lazy? For naive phase, we could pre-compute the conditional probabilities. We could pre-compute the conditional probability. Agree? But for K&N, no pre-computation at all. Can you pre-compute the distance? No, you don't even know what's the data point you want to check. That means in this example, the red dot. You don't even have the red dot.
ready beforehand, then no pre-computation could be done, right? So that's why we say that KNN is a lazy algorithm because no pre-computation could be done. You cannot pre-compute information beforehand. Lazy! Is it okay? Okay, KNN is a non-parametric algorithm. What does it mean by non-parametric? Non-parametric. That means no assumption.
Naive base. You make naive assumption. I are given certain belief. All the evidence are independent. This is one assumption. They contribute to the outcome equally, right? Another assumption. Naive base, many assumptions. But KNN, no assumption at all. No assumption, that means non-parametric. Non-parametric. Non-parametric. Okay? Yes. Very good.
Very good question. A+++. Your fellow classmate said the unit of the input matters, right? Maybe one is very small and another one is big. That is unfair. Very true. So that's why we are going to do one thing called standardization later on. We will try to standardize the data. Yeah, this is a very good question. All right. But let's talk about it later. But do you know?
What does it mean by lazy algorithm? Lazy means no precomputation. Non-parametric means no assumptions. By the way, no assumptions. Good or bad? Good or bad? Could be good, right? We don't need to make naive assumptions. Not very restrictive. Yeah, could be good. But lazy algorithm, is it good? No. Why? Lazy algorithm, that means no precomputation. No precomputation, that means...
.
But in terms of speed, which one runs faster? Naive Bay is very good. So that's why we need to introduce you many different algorithms, right? Because the different algorithms, pros and cons could be different. If there is one that is the best at all time, then what's the point for you to learn more, right? Just learn the one that works best all the time. Then that would be enough, right?
Okay. Okay. What are the steps for KNN? Okay, nearest neighbors? Six steps. Let me go through all of them. First one, prepare the training data and the test data. Training data, that means the labeled data set. Right? Test data. Let's say you have something to check. Something like new patient. Okay? Test data.
And then you need to pick a value of k. You need to pick it. Okay, and then determine which distance function to be used. As mentioned, there are many different choices of distance. Okay, and then compute the distances between the new data and all the training data. And then sort the distance and then assign the test sample based on the majority voting of the k nearest neighbors. You may say, Desmond.
Yeah, it seems like this is quite doable, but could you show me a real example? Yes. Okay, but before I talk about it, let me show you. Parametric model, what does it mean? You make assumption. Example, naive Bayes. Non-parametric model, no assumption. Example, KNN. Okay? So this table, we want to compare
two different models or approaches parametric model non-parametric model but this is something easy to understand that means one you need to make assumption that is parametric no assumption non-parametric okay haha hey this is the problem we want to tackle right t-shirt problem input height and weight two values that means 2d points
Right? We also know the expected output. M or L. That is category, right? Okay, now, given this number of customer data, how many? 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. 9 customers here. Another 9 here. So, altogether, there are 18 customers. We know their height and weight. 18 points.
18 points, 18 2D points. Okay, and then now I have a new customer. Yeah, this guy 161 cm height and weight 61 kilogram. I want to know what is the t-shirt size for this guy. Okay, is it okay? We have a training data. That means label data set in hand. We have the test data.
the new customer data. Okay, in KNN, what is the value of K? Let's pick K equal to 5. Hey, why we pick 5? I don't know. But one of the good reasons would be an odd number. Hey, by the way, how many categories do we have in terms of the output? Two, right? M or L. M or L. Two categories.
If the output is two category, I should pick k as an odd number. You may say, Desmina, you could pick one. I know. Yes, no problem. And you could pick three. Yes, but this time we pick five. Give me five. Is it okay? Good. All right, next. Determine which distance function to use. This one.
Whoa, Desmond, you said that naive Bayes would be the most difficult one in terms of math, right? I think this is very difficult. Not really. Everyone, training data, we call it X. Why? Bolded training data. How come bolded? Because each training data point, each training data point X.
With a number of values. It's just like the t-shirt problem. Just like the t-shirt problem. Each input data point. How many values? Two, right? Height and weight. Height and weight. Height and weight. So x here means, x train here means, the input data point of the training data set. How come it is bolded? Because each point with multiple values.
For the t-shirt problem, two values, height and weight. Okay, how about test data point? Exactly the same number of values. Because it's test. Using the t-shirt example, the new customer also weights and height. Height and weight. Agree? Okay, then distance. The first value minus...
the first value, take square, second value minus second value, take square, keep doing the same thing, last value minus the last value square, add them up, take square root. This is the decent formula that you have been using. I think you used this one in high school, right? By the way, by the way, by the way, like this, x1, y1.
How to compute the distance? square square square root. This is the distance formula that you used in high school, right? But how come this is more complicated? Because apart from two values, we could have many, many values, right? But actually, they are the same.
We call this Euclidean distance. Euclidean distance. Actually, the distance formula you have been using, we call it Euclidean distance. So in the examination, if I say that you need to use Euclidean distance, then you know what to use. Is it okay? Euclidean distance. Euclidean. Oh, you don't care. Good. Okay. What's next? Oh, compute the distance.
between the new customer data and all the data points in the label data set. Wow, everyone, the new customer data height 161, weight 61. And for the data points in the label data set, this is the first one, second one, third one, fourth one, fifth one, last one, agree? Okay.
And then we compute the distance between each point, between each point in the data set and the new one. Hey, can we do one? I will only do one. But if you want me to do all 18, I can do it. But please say no. Chinese New Year, right? Year of the horse. Okay, this one, huh? Compute this one and this one.
Let's say 161 minus, this is height, minus 158 squared, plus 61, and then minus 58 squared, square root. Agree? Okay, what is this? Don't scare me. Three, three square? Nine. This one? Three square? Nine.
Square root of 18, believe me, 4.24. Then we repeat the same thing for all the remaining points in the label dataset. Okay? Obviously, you should do this using Python. Ha, but in the exam, good luck. In the exam? Can I use a computer? No. Should we do it manually? Yes.
Can I use a calculator? Yes, but only the one labeled Hong Kong EAA approved All right, that means those are ordinary one. Don't use iPhone. Don't use Android Okay, and no smart glasses. I know now is the day Yeah, technologies right very good 8.2 Hmm, we will check your glasses and you can check mine. No worry
Ordinary one. Okay? Yes, all the distances are computed. What's next? Sort them. I sort them in ascending order or descending order. K nearest neighbors. You only care about those smaller distance values, right? K nearest neighbors. So if I were Yoke,
I will sort them in ascending order. Ascending order. That means from smaller to larger. From smaller to larger. Okay, I sort them already. Five nearest neighbors, right? So I only care about the five nearest one. These five. Okay, everyone. Hey, five nearest neighbor already. Yeah? And then we do majority voting, right? Everyone.
Then what should we say for the new customer? We should give what size of T-shirt to the new customer? Well, among the five, four of them, medium size. One of them, large size, right? Then we should give the medium size T-shirt to the new guy. Is it okay? Very simple. By the way, now you believe, right? K&N is easy compared to
Naive base. But sorry, you need to tackle lab two. Lab two will be about naive base. How about lab three? K and N. All right. Okay. And then we do majority voting. Only focus on these five. As mentioned, four of them, medium size. One of them, large size. Let's follow the majority. Medium.
Very simple. Very easy. Okay. In the exam, I may ask you this question. What if I pick k equal to 4? If I pick k equal to 4, you may get a tie. But in this situation, even you get k equal to 4, is it problematic? No, right? Does it mean that this is good? No. Right?
For this particular example, you may say, well, even I pick K equal to four is good enough, Desmond. I know you're lucky. Yeah. But if I give you another test point, you may not get something similar. You may get a tie. Yeah. Four nearest neighbors. Two, maybe medium, two, maybe large. Then you GG. Do you know what I'm saying, everyone? We will ask you some open question in the exam.
That means that based on the data, we ask you what happened for this? What happened for that? This is what we mean by understanding. Is it okay? Yeah? But pick K equal to 5. Definitely safe. Odd number. No tie. There should be a winner. Right? Okay. And good. Do you know what I am saying? I know you are still in holiday mood. Me too. Yeah.
I hope next week more students will come. Yeah, it's a bit embarrassing, right? I think today only 20% of you guys are here. But good, thanks for coming. No worries, I think you guys would get A plus or A and leave all the remaining ones to other students. I'm sorry. Oh, okay, good. Hey, oh no, my goodness.
I need to ask a way rule to fix it. You see? Out of the boundary. Out of the boundary. Yeah, no good. So that's why I've been using 16 to 9, right? And for those of you who took my 102 free course, you know I have been using 16 to 9, right? Lecture slide. And this is the beauty. Anyway, I shouldn't complain. Okay, anyway.
Okay, you know the idea of KNN. Now it's time for me to show you how to implement it. By the way, are we going to build KNN from scratch using NumPy? No. Take a look. Which library do we use? SKLearn. PsykinLearn again. Desmond. Why?
Because if you use Psyche Learn, that means we are the ones to implement that using NumPy. Very true. Very true. You see, we are good guys. And we are bad guys at the same time. Right? Because in the lecture notes, if we show you how to implement the algorithm using a very sophisticated library, then we give you a hard time. You need to do exactly the same thing using NumPy. Build it from scratch. Sorry. I apologize.
Okay, how many of you took 102.3? Very good. Do you still remember I introduced you one thing called all pair distances? At the end of the NumPy lecture notes, I show you an example demonstrating how to compute all pair distances using NumPy, no loop. Do you think that one is useful to tackle KNN? Yes. This is the reason why we introduced you
that last semester. Ah, now you enjoy your life, just grab it. No full look, no wow look, done. Yes. Hey, no worry, because for those of you who went to the tutorial in the first two weeks, I think you have seen that one also, right? Hey, no worry, that algorithm is very useful to compute all pair distances. Okay, anyway, everyone, show time.
Okay, from scikit-learn.preprocessing, import label encoder. So what does it mean? There is a folder called scikit-learn in Python. In this folder, there is a module or PY file called preprocessing. And in this PY file, there is a class called label encoder. We will use this class later on.
Okay, one more time. There is a folder called scikit-learn in Python. In this folder, there is a PY file called preprocessing. And in this PY file, there is a class called label encoder. We will use it later on. Okay, next one. From scikit-learn.neighbors, import k-neighbors classifier. Again, there is a folder called scikit-learn.
In this folder, there is a PY file called neighbors. In this file, there is a class called Kneighbors classifier. And this guy is for us to deal with the problem using KNN. Is it okay? All right. Okay. Wow, your good friend. Import NumPy as MP. How come, Desmond? Are we going to use NumPy? Yes.
We only use NumPy to store the input data and then the labels. Okay? I'm not going to implement this from scratch. I just use NumPy to store the data. All right? Okay. Show time. I create the first NumPy array called height with all the heights of the customers. 1D or 2D array? 1D.
Right? One D array with all the heights of the customer. Another number array, weights, with all the heights of the customers. One more number array, size, with all the expected output of the customers. That means t-shirt size. Three number arrays, height, weight, and t-shirt size. Right?
Easy? Okay, now, I create an object, label encoder type, encoder. What is this, Desmond? I use this object to call the method bit transform, bit transform, bit transform, to transform the size to numbers. Size, M or L, right? M or L, right?
I want to convert M or L to numbers. But I don't do it manually. I use fit transform to do it. Do you know what I'm saying, everyone? Do you know what I'm saying? So at the end of the day, all the size will be converted to numbers. No more M, no more L. Convert all of them to numbers. Okay? And then I will tell you why we do that later on. Okay. And then...
Sip them together. What does it mean by sip them together? Bundle them together. Bundle height and weight together. Bundle these two guys together, these two guys together, these two guys together, these two guys together, these two guys together. That means I bundle the height and weight together. All right? So sip function is a tool for you to bundle the data together. Okay? The first height and then first weight.
bundle them. Second height, second weight, bundle them, et cetera, et cetera. All right. And then I convert the resulting stuff to list. Python list. What is it for? To manipulate the data easily. Later on. Okay, now, show time. Hey, neighbors classifier. This is the guy that we used to do KNN, right?
I use the class kNeighborsClassifier to create an object model. But you need to pass one thing to underscore, underscore, unit, underscore, underscore of a kNeighborsClassifier. Everyone, what is it? What do we pass? What do we pass to underscore, underscore, unit, underscore, underscore of kNeighborsClassifier? The value of k. What is it? Why?
Why five? Because we used five earlier. Right? Okay. Now, how to pass the labeled dataset to this guy? Use the kNeighborsClassifyObject.fit method. Okay. Let me give you all the inputs, features. That means the bundled input. Right?
and also give you the corresponding labels. Now, I pass you the label dataset. Label dataset means input and the corresponding output. Is it okay? Okay, now, we are ready to answer the question. Well, K&N, do predict for me the new customer with height 161, weight 61. Tell me what should be the t-shirt size.
Is it okay? By the way, by the way, attention. 1D or 2D? 2D. Why 2D? This is live. If you use Scikit Learn to do KNN, then the test sample has to be 2D. This is live. Okay, the result is predicted. Everyone predicted. Is it a number or M or L?
You convert all the labels from M, L to numbers, right? So the one that you get back will be a number. But you don't like it, right? So you need to do conversion. Convert it back to M or L. How? Encoder. That means this guy. .inverse transform method. Pass this guy the predicted result. Hey, this is...
M or L? M or L? Okay, print it. Very easy. Very easy. What is the output? The one that we calculated earlier. Based on 5NN. 5 nearest neighbor. What should be the output? M or L? M, right? If you don't believe, please say, I don't believe you. Then you need to run this program at home and see whether you get M. If you get L, interesting. Talk to me. Is it okay? Yeah? By the way,
Later on, if we ask you to do KNN in programming assignment 1. Huh? Programming assignment 1, Desmond? Yes, it's coming. If we ask you to do KNN in PA1, you need to build it from scratch using Lumpai. But it's always a good idea to check your answer using Scikit-learn. You must do it. Very easy to use. One page of code. Just make changes, right?
Feed in the new data and see what happened. That's the trick. Is it okay? Happy? Okay. Shut up. Have a nice weekend. Weekend, huh? Tomorrow is a Saturday. Enjoy. Yeah. Continue to celebrate. Okay. Thank you very much. See you next week. Thank you.